John Philip Clum collection, 1874-1917
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
John Philip Clum collection, 1874-1917
MS 284
Clum, John Philip, 1851-1932
The John P. Clum collection is divided into two subgroups: records of Clum's tenure at the San Carlos Apache Indian Agency, 1874-1878, and documents relating to his career, 1880-1917 chronological arrangement. This collection includes, photocopies of San Carlos Indian Agency reports, abstracts of disbursements, vouchers, accounts current, and auditor's reports pertaining to Clum's work at the Agency from 1874-1878. Also information and correspondence regarding his employment from 1880-1917 in the War Dept. and the Post Office Dept., as well as his lecture tours for the Southern Pacific Railroad.
.8 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Born on 1 September 1851 near Claverack in the Hudson Valley of New York, John Philip Clum attended Rutgers University, but dropped out of college for health reasons and came West. Arriving in Santa Fe in 1871, he soon became a government astronomical observer with the Signal Corps. From 1874 until 1877, Clum served as Apache agent on the San Carlos Indian Reservation in Arizona Territory.
He adeptly handled the Apache outbreaks from the reservation by asking the military to withdraw to a distance of five miles from the reservation. To limit confrontations between the Apaches and the nearby settlers, Clum helped the Indians to implement agricultural pursuits which would make them self-supporting. He also encouraged them to set up their own law enforcement and judicial systems. As a result of these practices, Clum succeeded in converting many of the Apaches to a more sedentary existence. It was his Apache police force which tracked and captured Geronimo in 1877. Clum soon became a victim of the political situation in Washington. The Indian Commissioner had given the Army permission to once again come onto the San Carlos Reservation. Discouraged by the government's indifferent and unfair treatment of his Indian charges, Clum protested to Washington, and resigned from the Service when his objections were ignored.
In 1877, Clum became editor of the Tucson Citizen. In 1886, after three years as editor of the Citizen, Clum founded and became the first editor of the Tombstone Epitaph, having been attracted to that town by news of the rich silver strike there. Besides publishing the Tombstone Epitaph, Clum was elected Mayor of Tombstone and was appointed Postmaster from 1884-1886.
Clum went to work for the U.S. Postal Service in Washington, D.C. in the late 1880s, but in the early 1890s, he was out west again, serving as Postal Inspector in the western judicial district of Texas. On 5 March 1898, Clum was appointed Post Office Inspector for the Territory of Alaska and charged with the organization and extension of the postal service there. He retired from this post in 1908.
After his retirement, John P. Clum traveled a great deal. A fine speaker, he was employed by the Southern Pacific Railroad as a lecturer. Also, Clum began to write his memoirs, which, after his death, his son Woodworth completed. The resulting book, Apache Agent, was later made into the motion picture, Walk the Proud Land, starring Audie Murphy.
John P. Clum died of a heart attack 3 May 1932 at the age of 81.
Organization
This collection is organized into two subgroups:
Subgroup I: Records of John P. Clum, San Carlos Apache Indian Agency, 1874-1878
Subgroup II: Career Documents of John P. Clum, 1880-1917
Scope and Content Note
Collection, 1874-1917, relating to the financial records and letters kept by the Office of Indian Affairs, the Post Office Department, and the War Department regarding John Philip Clum, and used by Wallace E. Clayton, co-owner of the Tombstone Epitaph, in researching the life of Clum, the founder and first editor of the Epitaph.
The Records include photocopies of San Carlos Indian Agency reports, abstracts of disbursements, vouchers, accounts current, and auditor's reports pertaining to Clum's work at the Agency from 1874 to 1878.
The Career Documents contain information regarding Clum's employment in the War Department and the Post Office Department as well as with the Southern Pacific Railroad. Of interest are photocopies of information documenting Clum's desire to re-enter government service with the Office of Indian Affairs beginning in 1912. Included is a letter in his behalf from Arizona Senator Mark A. Smith.
This material was collected by Wallace E. Clayton, co-owner of the Tombstone Epitaph, in researching the life of Clum, founder and first editor of the paper.
Access Terms
Clum, John P., 1851-1932 -- Archives
United States. Office of Indian Affairs -- History -- 19th century
Apache Indians -- Government relations
Frontier and pioneer life -- Arizona
Indian agents -- Arizona
Arizona -- History -- Sources
San Carlos Indian Reservation (Ariz.) -- History
Correspondence
Reports
Related Material
For related items, see the papers of John P. Clum (AZ 003).
Container List
- Subgroup I: Records of John P. Clum, San Carlos Apache Indian Agency, 1874-1878
  Contains photocopied information, including abstracts of disbursements, vouchers, statements of current accounts, reports of employees, information on Clum's accounts examined and allowed by the Office of Indian Affairs, remarks made in the Office of the Commissioner of Indian Affairs regarding these accounts, and Clum's explanations of the accounts when so requested. There are several photocopies of interest, including a letter to Clum from Edward P. Smith, Commissioner, written on 27 March 1874 to notify Clum of his appointment as Special Indian agent for the Indians of the San Carlos Agency in Arizona Territory; a letter from the Secretary of the Treasury speaking of Agent James E. Roberts, the Camp Apache Indian Agent who was relieved by John P. Clum; and correspondence regarding the employment of George A. Clum, his brother, as a teacher.
  Also included are photocopied documents questioning Clum's use of funds as well as his justifications of the expenses. A final item of note is a photocopy of Clum's last report as Indian Agent, dated 18 September 1877. The span dates of some of the documents overlap because they are summary reports.
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 3rd quarter. 1874 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 4th quarter. 1874 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 3rd and 4th quarters. 1874 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 1st and 2nd quarters. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 1st quarter. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 2nd quarter. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 3rd quarter. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 4th quarter. 1875 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 1st quarter. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 2nd quarter. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 3rd quarter. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 4th quarter. 1876 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 3rd quarter 1874 - 4th quarter 1876. 1874-1876 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 1st and 2nd quarters. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 3rd quarter. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records, 4th quarter. 1877 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records. 1874-1877 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - San Carlos Apache Indian Agency records. 1878 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Subgroup II: Career Documents of John P. Clum, 1880-1917
  Contains photocopied information pertaining to Clum's career. Of note are photocopies of a letter to the Postmaster General from Clum, seeking his first government job; letters from 1912-1915 in which Clum sought reappointment as an Indian agent; a letter of recommendation in Clum's behalf from Arizona senator Mark A. Smith; a schedule of a lecture tour and newspaper clippings about Clum's lectures; and evidence of Clum's work for the War Department before he gained a transfer to the Post Office Department.
  - Postmaster, Tombstone, Arizona. 1880-1882 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Post Office Department, Washington, D.C. 1882-1884 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Service Record. 1882-1908 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - War Department. 1890-1891 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Post Office Department. 1891-1911 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Application for superintendency, Indian Service. 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Southern Pacific Railroad - Harriman Lines, lecture circuit. 1912-1917 (Box 2, Folder 13)